Thanks a lot
for having me here. It's a pleasure.
It's an honor to stay always here
and to join the community,
a community that I enjoy
and I like a lot. And.
Well, we are broadcasting from Mexico City
today.
We are going to present
the say on the future of writing, reading,
thoughts, meditation and walking.
The original name of the presentation
was synchronicities, but I guess
I assume that that's implicit as well
when you will walk.
So by walking I mean like
so you know
that this is a mobile experience.
So as an.
I mentioned before and.
Well we
recommend to use a mobile experience.
So this is a great moment.
If you have a mobile
to switch to your mobile
to look for your headphones
and to look or to think about safe
public space to to walk around. Right.
Especially a place without cars, because
that can be a little bit dangerous.
I know that in some cities
it's a little bit difficult to do that.
And of course, if you want to get
a nice drink, meanwhile you walk that.
That's perfect.
That's fantastic.
Meanwhile, by the time that you are doing
all that,
I will be presenting and continue
with the with the presentation.
So this experiment is divided
basically like in two moments,
like a brief ten minutes of presentation
about the topic of today.
This is an essay
that we are going to write all together.
And it's a collaborative
writing like experiment
where different provocations
or imaginaries
will rise to invite us to think
and to talk and to about it,
or to raise questions as well.
And so this is the link
for the mobile experience.
I will also.
Woop woop woop.
I also put it here on the.
Okay,
wait a minute.
Okay. Here
I will also place it here in the chat
and okay, wait a minute.
I never thought about this.
So where is soon?
We are here chat, chat and.
Okay, perfect.
Here is the chat
so I will place it here. So.
You can join also by the desktop computer.
But let me tell you that it's going to be
a completely different experience.
The ones that you have on the desktop
that the one that you have
on the mobile device
and the one that you have on desktop.
Unfortunately,
it doesn't include any captions
or any transcriptions about the text
or what people is saying,
and I try to respect the original language
from the different interviewers
or different imaginaries of the project.
So let me tell you more about the project.
The project was inspired on this book
that calls the McInally cantar
that it was published in 1967
by Gabriel Said Here in Mexico City.
And it's an essay
about the future of language,
about the future of poetry and writing,
about the future of.
He talked about one Bush,
for instance, and and he
of course, he's all the time
speculating about the future of language.
And he even like making
a mathematical mathematics about
how to be a sonnet, you know, how many
combinations and blah, blah, blah, right?
But something that really triggers to me
to do this project is this,
this, this part where he said, reading
a poem is writing it.
However, writing it for the first time,
making the master program is not the same
as continue to write in each time
it is read.
So by this here lute or here
both to the idea of the reader, right
that the territory itself,
it remembers me that literature or art
doesn't exist if it's not the code,
if it's not written by somebody else.
So you might have this huge
combination of poetry,
you know, with thousands of words,
you know, combine it in the basis.
But at the end,
if those are not interpreted
by the reader,
you know, that's basically nothing.
And so, yeah,
I say I have to do something with this.
And, and I did like a small iteration
back in those days.
We have like this presentation about
that I call a sign on writing of reading
some possible Futures with Monica, Lola,
Ryan, Noel and Nick Montfort here
in Mexico City at the Seven L's Across
America Poetry Colloquium
at the University of Cloud.
And well, the main idea was to have
all those imaginaries
in some sort of a sonnet.
This is my sonnet, right?
So I call for other people
from other imaginaries,
you know, and I asked them
what would be the future of language.
Right.
I invite especially to poets,
to calligraphers, programmers,
and to different language
artists, people that were working with,
writing as a mother in their
in their art expression and
coming from different communities
around the globe,
from the, you know, from Belgium,
from the Netherlands, from Argentina
and from Portugal, from the States.
So the main idea was to have like this
imaginaries, right?
There were not,
of course, a right answer.
It was more about the imagination
from their own perspective
and from their field.
How could be the future of language?
And so the idea was during
the presentations, the presentations,
the other artists, such as Monica
and Lola and Nick will answer or will
talk about those imaginaries.
You know, I was looking
also to understand more the dynamics,
you know,
that could happen with this social event.
It was a little bit messy, to be honest.
You can access through this code,
QR code.
And but then I realized, you know,
that this project was even bigger
because of course, the kind of answers
that the people were bringing
were different possibilities
about the future that we can explore.
You know, about what it is happening in
reading and writing
or a little bit to understand more.
And so I was invited to also
to give like this a participatory talk.
So I present the same, you know, like
say some writing and reading thoughts
simulators during this exploration
that happened
in, in Chile in the University of Chile
was invited by Unesco.
Slack.
Basically, we present a little bit
of the history of AI, you know,
looking for especially text
generators, you know,
so we want, of course, romance novels,
you know, coming from basically the middle
age, this amazing device.
We also talk, of
course, about the meeting of of Dartmouth.
You know, we talk about the artificial
versified of the school boys,
you know, this sort of Latin combinatory
poem
that was basically done
in, in the Victorian
England by John Peter, 1677.
And then, of course, it was remaking
by the Latin verse of machine
in the 19th century by John Kirk.
I won't play the video,
but you can search it on the web.
And it's amazing
how they create this sort of mechanics.
And I can imagine the people,
you know, in front of this machine, just
printing all these poems
and thinking that the machine was alive.
So the idea that the machine was alive
or was thinking, you know,
it has been there, I guess, since
the people were printing books as well. So
part of this
presentation was as well to to
rethink about
AI more as a simulator of thinking
rather than an intelligence right,
that the people
that were getting inspired about,
how can they simulate thinking.
But this was not about that.
The AI was thinking itself.
So in the next iteration, I was embedded
in the International Conference
of Visual Poetry Peru.
And and it was about the same.
In this case.
We were looking for strategies
and devices for imagination.
So of course we talk about the like
how to make data is poem
by Tristan Tzara, right?
That is basically instructions are very
instructive, a way to provoke writing.
We talk about the Poema proceso, right
by by Vladimir Diaz Pinto and Adisa
from Brazil,
you know, and different types of agencies
that were provoking to create
a those poetries
of those informational text.
Others, such as the performance of Korean
and love story
that were more like a locative narratives.
So different kind of strategies
that during the history the people were
especially like in the avant garde,
they were creating to provoke
a writing or generate text.
So now, today,
the idea of this exploration is about how
how fault simulators affects writing
and so thought forms.
Okay, so I'm looking for.
Wait a minute,
I just lost myself
between all those windows.
Okay,
so during the 20th century
there excited idea
of bringing visual epistemology
to the needs of the industrialized society
that was developing back in those days,
the role was to bring visual semantics
and six stacks to be so language.
This is more developed by Johanna
Drucker in graphics
in the first chapter, for instance.
So the role was to bring visual semantics
and syntax to be so language.
As designers,
I can tell you there are a lot.
For example,
the base of design and line up form by the
by Walter Crane,
the Grammar of Ornaments by Owen Jones,
or previous point and line
by the Kandinsky,
design and visual communication by Bruno
Arbus.
The interaction of colors, vote and forms
by any pencil and CD
Libert.
So Thoughtful Forms is a book
that is a very rare book
between all those ones,
because the other ones.
This is sort of thought
forms in 1905 1905.
Is that the save the visual essays?
So all the other books were focused
about the how to do semantics
to an industrial society,
right to, to design, for instance.
But in the case of this book,
this is focused on bringing this
visual semantics
to a theological or philosophical
perspective.
So you might know a little bit
more about this.
Helena Blavatsky was founder of this
Theosophical association. Right.
And it was was a woman in London
or an Englishwoman, a prominent,
well studied.
She studied science. She studied botanic.
She fight for secularism in England.
She studied philosophy.
She was Marxist.
She was a feminist.
And there is a moment in her career
that she said,
you know, I want to go in this
Theosophical theosophy ideas.
That was assistant to embrace
what they see as essential
to truth underlying religion,
philosophy and science.
You know,
some people say it was about religion.
Some people were saying
it was about occultism.
Right?
It was more about,
I think about that perspective.
So they were looking to represent aura,
right, or all those kind of topics.
In the case of little bit Lit Bitter,
he was a prize from the Church of England.
He was a spiritual spiritualist. And.
So both
of them were traveling a lot to India.
And they were inspired
and bringing a lot of methodologies
to meditate
or to have clarification views.
And with those they were exploring
different topics of chemistry,
for instance.
So they were looking for instance,
for the atoms, right?
They were describing the atom itself.
They described the quantum.
That's that was very weird.
And of course, you know,
back in those days,
like the people were saying like this,
this guys are completely out of the
out of the topic.
You know, they are completely crazy.
Besides that,
they have a lot of followers as well.
During the book, they define and depict
a visionary methodologies
for the invisible world
on the spirituality realm,
and realizing
that tool of the power of their thoughts
acts as a stimulus of novel
and group base.
How thoughts affect aura, for instance.
So imagine like that.
There is these people
that are making this bizarre like say,
or methodologies,
but more about to think about
the power of the thought,
the power about thinking.
Right. And the
so they they divide it
basically in three different lines
that to determine to to to create this.
And it was like the quality of,
to determine colors, the nature of thought
to that in mind,
the forms and the fitness of thoughts
to the demand, a clearness of online.
So part of the importance of this book
is that this book inspires, well, people
such as Kandinsky, who also wrote a book
like bringing all those visual stimuli.
In the case of concerning this 312 art
that is also very philosophical,
or in the case of point,
line and plane later on in the 30s.
But, and this is, it is
it is interesting in the case
that abstraction art,
most of the times focus as a mother,
you know, but it doesn't realize that,
at least from the perspective
it was talking back
about the spiritual right,
the spiritual of of the people, the hours
they were saying, for instance,
that part of the breaking point
is this, this,
this painter, the Lady of Moscow.
Or they can see
like an expressionism, right?
And they also can see,
like some of the theories
that were in concerning the spiritual art.
If you can see the time it was 1920
when it was done, the Lady of Moscow
and the Concerning
the Spiritual Art was published in 1911.
The book of that were inspired,
the Thoughts and forms
was at the beginning of the 1905.
So there were some sort of linked right.
And part of the of, of
if you think about time, you know,
like it was, I think a very similar time
that we are living in a way.
Right.
Think about like what
the photography was back in those days.
You know, what technology
was meaning back in those days,
even if you think about, for instance,
in literature
coming from,
I don't know, from circle and all in, in,
in Sherlock Holmes, you know,
all the time it's about this fight
between speculative rationality, right?
That is the modern world
and all these spiritualism,
occultism
that were in the on the other side.
Right.
So it is talking about
also about the ontology
of the things. And
so especially I think in the, in the,
in the West culture,
it was like completely
like a breaking point.
And so and that's what I
that's why I also took this
or I choose this book
a little bit to understand more
or to look back to calligraphy
and to Asia.
So I decided that thoughts forms
are also symbols.
And maybe there is a moment of history
that we forgot,
like this other side.
And so in this case it's like it's a,
it's a Iranian poem,
you know, wrote by Rumi, the calligrapher.
It is Golden Hossein clan
that is basically like the shift of
of calligraphy nowadays in Iran.
It says you have blue glass
in front of your eyes,
causing
you work to be blue or to turn blue.
Something
that I didn't know, for instance,
was that the calligrapher is,
of course, an artist is a poet as well,
but he's also interpreting other poems
coming from other times.
So in this other case
is no one seeks rules and gems.
Otherwise
the sun is still at work in the mind.
And the query,
just as it was, as always, was.
This was done by Hafiz.
So all those poems were writing in
in a style of calligraphy named nostalgic
that was done for Persian,
and it was done by Mir Ali Davidson.
It features or characterized
by the vertical strokes
that remains, the trees and the flowers,
the wrong curves, the undulations
and hills,
the allegations, fields
and planes, the musical powers,
the Cincinnati,
the letters, the body contours of animals
so that the shape of the of the poem
itself, most of the times remains.
Animals,
especially birds and especially humans.
And it is very funny because part of how
this style of calligraphy
born was because a
Malay, Ali himself,
the creator, had dream in which Ali,
the son in the law of the Prophet
Muhammad, appeared to him
and guide him to draw
letters
that look like wings of flying geese.
According to this legend,
he envisioned geese whose wings
and soaring movement
called to mind the shape of letters.
So if you see if we see back,
this also has a style
that most of the time is hanging.
All the letters are kind of like hanging.
But here, you know, like
there is if you see the shape,
there is a strong reminiscence,
you know, for instance, to beards.
And when you say, for instance, the birds,
you know,
in what means birds
in, in the Iranian culture,
you know, they have a lot of mythology
with beards, for instance, humor,
the bits of fortune in the Paradise,
a symbol of prosperity rock
here, beards that were eating elephants
or that carry elephants
and simmered.
Who talks predicts teach
prophet is a wise
beard is a leap
that many years that repeat,
such as the Venice is a messenger
between the sky and the earth.
And this is something that happened
a lot in symbolism with the bird.
The bird became like a messenger,
you know, that were all the time,
you know, the people
didn't knew where it was, you know.
So they thought they were messengers
between the earth
and the entities and that are flying.
So from
this perspective, birds are messenger
between the earth and the skies,
the mother and the interior,
the idea and the link
as the Iranian poetry,
the shape and visual
disposition of the elements
are the container of the poem and the poem
itself, such as a calligraphy.
The National League style
induce a peaceful result,
but it is a calligraphy
sensibility, skills and inner
connection with the outer space
that make the symbol possible.
In the words of the frame
of my Iranian friend,
that's a friend that I have, Alyssa.
It's a spiritual journey.
So if literature implies that the reader,
the poem exists when we decoded,
the poet is just a messenger,
such as the bird.
So for me,
it's very important
to bring a life that the
writing goes
beyond right of typing.
Writing for a lot of tradition is drawing.
It's something visual,
which implies a meditation, which implies
a connection
with the with the environment.
And this is something that happened a lot,
especially on the East traditions
on calligraphy in the case.
This is the case of, of of,
of Iranian calligraphy.
But of course there are more when you go
to China or when you go to Japan, right.
When they do have their own perspective
on their understanding of the flow,
for instance, or energy,
which make possible.
This practice is something that
that at least you know, it's a
as a writer,
you know, it's difficult to to understand.
For instance, I was talking
also with the friend, very good friend
from the Netherlands, you know,
he do the war and he was a little bit
concerned about that, you know,
like what means writing today,
you know, when you are losing identity
because the mistake for him,
for most of the calligraphers,
it's important.
It is like a shape of the identity
of the people.
I will stop here because I can just go on
and I don't think it's really necessary.
And I would like to pass
to the other side of the presentation.
I hope that
everybody
have already gone and walk around.
Let me know if it is true
if that happened, by the way.
So if you did, you need to walk
and you need to walk around 200 step.
And once you get in a line
on the display on the screen,
share your screen with us and play it
at the end of the audio.
Please reply back and
but or place
a question about the imaginary.
Okay, let me see.
We have some question here.
Oh yeah,
thanks a lot.
Jennifer.
So let me know how many people have gone.
Maybe I will do it also the same.
By the way, I need to to walk.
Often.
If you have any question
or you have any input
or you want to share something about what
I have said, please let me know.
Thank you.
Thanks to you, Peter and.
No walking to the air quality.
Terrible. I live in a wildfire smoke here.
Okay.
No problem.
Let me see.
Have John Murray we have.
Okay, so.
Yep. Brian is here.
Sadly the same.
Okay, I will teach you.
I mean, let me now share.
I'm sorry. Pulling outside. It's okay.
No problem.
But in progress.
Oh my God. Oh.
So I will show you
how to hack this, right?
Because otherwise you won't be able to
to know
what is happening
with the other people around.
So if you can open the website on your.
Mobile device, let me know.
Stop sharing.
Okay.
Okay okay.
So if you open the website
I'm doing jumping hacks.
If you open the website on your phone.
La la la la la.
I did just pink bland.
You got a pink man. Yes, please.
Hi, Heidi.
Now open it.
Just click on that.
And if you can share,
can you share the your screen?
Oh, yes.
Exactly.
I got a pink band.
I can't go very far from my computer,
so I was just walking back and forth.
Okay. Now I wish I would.
I will let you know how it works.
I mean, it's so you open it, right?
You will have like a screen like this.
You say allow right.
And as we are not going to walk
for somebody,
a lot of people cannot go outside.
Just take it and shake it.
But you will have to shake it
a lot, right?
I have an audio file playing.
Oh yeah.
We'll increase our capacity
to reference citations,
index all kinds of materials and
syntactic leaps.
But there will be moments
when we are writing or speaking,
when we will suddenly go to say something,
and what will happen will be
a blank, because what we were going to say
is prohibited.
Prohibited by rules
to which we do not have access. The.
These will be the rules of a new lung
that governs apparel.
But in addition to this,
I see the increased field
of poetic expression
and linguistic expression more broadly,
within which poetics occupies
a particular figured place,
increasing to the point
where every possibility is intensified
that we have a greater and greater
probability of any particular utterance
being able to be made and associations
with it.
The networks of connections, the resonance
through that linguistic
field will only intensify over time,
as every bit of language
that has ever been produced continues
to exist in a kind of plenum of space
time, where it is accessible, channeled
tunnels appears and may be used.
That's Johanna Drucker.
Yeah, I.
That's great.
And it's great.
It is.
It is
that.
You got something?
I think I got the same file
that PD was actually going through.
And then
mine has with the Christian bomb,
actually.
Oh, nice.
You got
because of my hearing,
I can't actually have sound on my phone.
Okay. But I can read it.
But through the writing of texts
drowning us in such a way
we could no longer breathe but communicate
among ourselves with other human beings.
About a year ago, Matt Kirschenbaum
predicted the arrival of the apocalypse
apocalypse text a future where this.
Oh dear, I've lost it now.
I clicked on the screen again
to make it brighter and I lost it.
So it's interesting
to see how quickly things go.
And it's an interesting
interface with the phone
now with just
like playing and with that text
and the sound,
the voice of of that woman,
I have to say, it's amazing.
It's a, it's a, it was a.
It was Alex.
Okay.
Somebody else got something. Yes.
Peter, you are right.
The phone doesn't work with location.
It's not checking your location.
It's checking your movement. Right.
So that's why we can do this.
And and you get, like, more.
But of course,
it was a matter of consumption
of of energy.
Right. Of of your phone as well.
Like I didn't want to
to track all the time
in order data and stuff like that
or your location.
So I will, I will place mine.
You know,
the idea of the future
has been totally captured.
Okay, let me see. What is the camera?
Well, it's in English, so we can I,
I would just oh my God.
Okay.
Let me check.
It's here.
Digitalis electronic.
Hello I'm Eugenio Tyseley
and for 25 years at the decay myself
to exploring the possibilities
of writing and digital technologies
or electronics
and similar mental story in.
Korea.
At this moment I am in a definite post
and I want to share some of this
about the future of writing.
In Scripture
karaoke.
I think it's important.
Give it the times that room
by to decouple our future
imagination
of supposed technological advance.
Important.
Concurrent.
Nuestros imaginaries de futebol
tecnologico.
Okay, I think that the idea of the future
has been totally captured by this idea
that technology is always offering us
new possibilities,
and that there are, for everything we do
at a cultural level, including writing,
is renew it by the hand of technology.
Idea of technology.
Siempre
nuevas tanto todo lo hacemos nivel
de la
nueva de la mémoire de la.
Is important.
I think that the coupling
these two phenomena is important
because how technology is perceived
is positioned
at this moment,
both at the political and social level.
Politico, nivel,
ambiental, social important, I think.
I think it's important
to do at the coupling.
And I think this idea of the new,
the future, that the future will always
be something new,
something on here of something
that have not imagined.
Futuro Nuevo Vito
imaginable.
Sentido.
It makes sense if we think of a linear
time, a linear, that progress
that goes in a fixed direction
and does not return.
Linear,
and I personally
like to think more of a circular time
where was already being can returned,
although in another way.
In the way.
And this and in fact
there will be perhaps more special time
because that has already been can return.
But if it returns in another way,
we can think of that the spirit of time.
So. Puede volver
manera.
So yo creo el futuro scriptura.
So I think that the future of writing
will not necessarily be something new,
something on here of something never seen,
but it will be something
perhaps that we have already seen.
You know, that we still see. No.
But that will return in a way
that will have new elements,
but not totally.
And my question to
you will be like which new forms
or return it?
Forms could happen.
Mixing the private ones
with the new technologies.
I don't know, it's just a question, right?
Like,
of course I think that some other practice
coming from the past are returning,
are coming back, and probably can get them
power by technology itself.
But yeah,
and there are many examples of that.
I was thinking, for instance,
about the performance of Dini.
You know, where she was like
kinetic making kinetic poetry.
You know, if I was trying to reframe that,
you know,
with calligraphy that is also very corpus.
So just just to give an example,
somebody else have a new exploration.
Yeah, that one is a good one.
Right.
How did you imagine
the future of writing and reading?
Jennifer.
How do you imagine it?
It wouldn't interact with me.
So when it's in portrait mode,
it just keeps looking.
I've been walking around my entire house,
shaking it, jumping up and down.
That's all I get.
It just looks like it's loading.
But then when I tilted the phone, then
I got the one line and I tried to tap it.
I tried to shake it.
Nothing happened.
Yeah, you can shake.
You cannot tap that one. That's just like
a prompt.
But that was as far as the phone got.
But no, you got you got it there.
You got it in the, in the,
in the vertical version there is a line.
But that line I have to say by the way,
that it has already been done.
It's a blank is.
Oh well you got to just say
just like the three points,
you know.
I have one from old format.
Maybe if you want to do what
you want me to play that one.
Yeah, please go for that.
I'm having futuro
del Rey de la lectura aspect.
Speculative aspect to Ya has
to be a continuous.
Primero. No.
Can you see it in.
Is it reversed for you? The video. Okay,
okay.
Gracias a la de la computation personal.
No internet
siguiente.
Podemos hablar de close
reading a la lectura.
Hacemos
microscopical textos para comprehension
no tenemos también
el tiempo de esta lectura.
Auxiliary a poor poor.
Sitios web poor busqueda, texto
e la machine reading no a la lectura
produce mapa verbal,
etc..
No todo esto
mas segunda
a empezar.
Todo mundo durante.
Son las intelligences.
Artificial intelligences a
production de texto tuna manera
current casi perfecta
no a in diversity mentions a.
La creativity Como la auto
todo esto bueno también potency
sensors por la de da semiotica
in the factores tecnologico
insidious en la textual
es el futuro de la escuela
desde el punto de vista de la
comunicacion. Sign
a speculative a través de la
la la la la poesia
perfecto. Wow.
Do you speak Spanish? Yes.
So I guess he's saying when if we're
thinking about the role of writing, which
is communication, and what would happen
if we were telepathic to poetry?
It was an interesting question
at the end. There.
That's good.
Yeah. Turn it right. Change it.
Because the other part is very, a very,
very economic.
Rodolfo Mata is visual poet,
an academic from Mexico City.
I have the honor to work also with him.
And, and he just brought
this idea of telepathy,
you know, like that also,
you know, go to the occultism site,
you know, to to the, to India, you know,
so what do you think?
What will happen to poetry
if we can communicate through the minds?
Well, if we were telepathic,
I wonder if we would still communicate
in, in word syntax.
Like,
like because I think so much of my own
like mental process is imagery
that I would probably be casting
like wow images rather than words to
if I were, if I would try to communicate
telepathically, which I think, like does
play out in like the way
that I express myself poetically, but
I think that that would be the next thing
is like, what is telepathic language?
It probably doesn't look like text
in the same way.
I don't know, it would just like
descriptive consciousness.
Yeah, absolutely.
But then it goes back
to this book of thought and forms, right,
that we're trying to do some sort
of visual language for telepathic,
you know, for this kind of process.
I wonder if you can standardize
this process, you know, like
if you can make like a the whole human
like thinking in the same visual way.
But but yeah, it's interesting
at least to, to to to think about it.
Like Alex said,
if we if we were telepathic,
what will happen to
poetry is such a provocative question.
Yes it is,
it is
especially also if you think,
for instance, about this idea of
coming from a concrete poetry,
like, like a poet, attention of things
in space time.
Right?
So like how,
how happened like the poem itself
with those imaginaries happening
that mentioned Edgar or Aura.
We were coming together.
We're probably will be more kinetic,
a language where we were just
understanding each other
without talking and like just flowing.
I don't know, like we we don't string it.
We were telepathic.
What would happen to poets such.
Yeah. Flower says.
Oh yeah.
There is like here
this the multiple presentation tests.
We don't think only in the mode
with multimodality
text visual sound, motion sense.
Okay.
So let's see if we can find another one.
Now is the campus shut out. Yes,
yes. Alex let's
okay.
So I have another one
okay okay I will play this in Spanish.
I'm sorry.
I probably won't go to for everything.
You got one in Firefox
okay I can, I can wait.
Just go for it.
Jennifer. No, no. It's fine.
You can play yours.
I got the audio that goes with
what is the future of writing and reading?
I can play it.
Yeah.
I don't know which one is that one,
but yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah.
And the ambas con un present un pasado
in la tecnologia con paradigms
affinis in principio del futuro
con un pasado original de un
donde no exist.
Maschine icon el collective
Como la expression oral con la escritura y
reproduction tecnologica in papyrus
codices o Imprenta
llega Como el principio
de auto con la subsequent in pronto
yo escribir porque see
porque puedo porque tengo acceso
a format tecnologico
de creation y también de reproduction Como
la Palma papel la imprenta Lauda Nader.
Why this de tiempo,
un principio monopolized
elitist traditionally masculine.
In your
commentary de la experiencia oral
muchas veces de incidences
feminine collector.
The information historias vuelve a replant
con la supuesto des
y del medio electronico
todavia de la elite local,
un proyecto fido,
la inteligencia artificial
collective
a utilizar lo Como veis de la expression
creative un resale de la.
Originally that oral pre-mRNA,
el futuro in pasado mutant
es el dia de expression
mas alla de la lettre
o variants ancestral, ahora es, etc.
El emoji la realidad virtual reality
bio implants
de Gino poetica
dentro de forma de interaction y Como
experiencia personalized.
Ya caso corporative.
Multiple interactive.
El cuerpo series Gregor y mercantilist.
La lecture series on experiencias
multiples de un yo colonization
y posthumous
transforming collaboration.
Oh quizas super a technological changes
presenta ahora tanto Como instrumental
Como Como
agent co-create ora y auto sustained
o c el yo de la escritura
de la lectura acaba por favor,
con su tables de illumination.
Pero también de calabro.
Entonces el principio de
de superstar
originally that impacto on lacto
tanto describer Como de la
o experimental literario redefining
qual saran Los nuevos paradigms
y practicas de creation
recombination infinity
in busca del plaza del conocimiento.
Oh, a caso solo del entry
y la distraction for multiplication.
The realities.
That's it.
I could see the English.
The English was underneath the Spanish.
So, Peter. Wow. That's great.
And that was Tina.
And what do you think about it?
What do you think about her nation?
Oh, there was so much.
And because I was holding the phone
toward my mic,
I didn't see the English
until the first few sentences had gone by.
And my Spanish is like
high school Spanish.
So I was a good eight words
behind everything she was saying.
There was a part at the beginning
and I think Peter captured it.
About the present?
Yeah, the present in the past
being separated.
But then there was
I have to think through this idea
of replication that coming up,
sort of replication in the collective
seem to be
two themes that were standing out to me.
Yes, she well, in a community,
even in Spanish, I think it's very depth.
It's like there is like a lot,
a lot to be said.
Right?
Like there is very critique,
you know, like about, well,
all the time is very critique
about those new technologies, you know.
But as I mentioned, Peter like her
question is more about
like how good new genders and means
when new realities multiplies.
What other ways of reading and writing
are out there?
Yeah, yeah.
Peter, jump!
No, I'm sorry.
I couldn't, like, translate it all
because it was really rich and. Yes.
That's a great I love Tina.
It's I'm going to I can I go back
and listen to these other recordings, like
just by going back through on my phone?
Yes, yes, you can go back like, well,
if you enter to the website
every time you enter to the
website, rearrange all those.
Different imaginaries.
Right.
So it might happen that it appears Tina
or probably will appeal Johanna right in
you Never knows.
Right?
And especially in this case, everybody,
each of us
will have like a different version.
So it might happen that it repeats
between our devices.
There is no like a hosting or like some,
some place
that is hosting
for the same experience to everybody.
So, so you know a little bit
more about the
what is behind.
But yeah.
Well all we know also coming back to Tina,
all we know
Tina and all we know more or less
like her way of thinking.
You know, she
she was here a little bit there,
but she she
I think she's in Spain and walking around.
Well, she didn't know that
it was about walking. But
somebody else have another one.
Can I record this one?
Send it to you later?
Yes, I think so.
I know there's going to be a link right
at some moment.
Okay.
So I'm going to play mine.
It's in Spanish and I,
I will just place it and please, God,
if you can just also help me a little bit,
I will appreciate it
because I know that it's also going
a little bit that,
Futuro.
Futuro in futuro.
And it is not
poetic as.
Poetic.
I don't see the singularity.
As tiempo segment on alphabets.
Several materiality.
So the technology incorporated supports
containment.
Definition.
Classical.
Support
decir del sonido definite incluso
I can.
Representation but
consistencies imaginary del sentido
del del 82.
What is the limit?
Poetical
and poetical.
Como.
Sin embargo
on Latin
de una.
Solo sylvan para
inducing un nautico.
Circuito de no.
Is impossible a representative.
De la tecnologias.
La valse de las inteligencia,
artificial personas
secreto.
P7. For the opacity relatively soon SEO
appropriate inclusion.
Calculable
para Los algorithm de la information.
I was just thinking of
what a great archive of these thinkers
voices this is and these
these these writers voices.
I was thinking about that
with the archival footage
that Deeney has at the next that that
that we have like these recordings
and including the recordings
of the conference that we have,
like not just the words of people,
but also their their like lived
voices, their embodiments
in a way, parts of it digitized.
Now, I think
it's something that I like a lot
about this walking experience, you know?
I mean, besides that, we didn't work
is about that this focus more on on
listening.
And when you listen, it, it
it connects in another way.
Even when we're listening to you
most of the time, I guess
I assume that you listen to Tina
in English, right?
Change a changed completely. Right.
And and this, this small nouns,
you know, like very fragile,
you know, textures of of meaning,
you know, that happened, you know,
in the silence or in the tone of voice.
You know, it's very, very interesting
in, in the case
of this was Claudio Manifesta
from Argentina.
He's a visual poet and he studied as well.
I mean, he teach a psychology, right?
But it's more like a luckless right.
And I can see it
and I can see it through this, you know,
and it's a
it's a lot to decipher in the way
he talks, even to me,
like listening in Spanish.
You know, it was listening once, twice,
you know, like trying to decode everything
what he's saying.
And that goes back
a lot in about identity, you know,
like about the self,
about the desire of the self.
And he say no, like there are I mean, yes,
there are lectures
that not even the machine
the self will acquire like those machines.
I mean in a way it
I cannot say it says that,
but it let you touch that at the end.
Right.
Or some other questions
that were placed, for instance, by Edgar.
You know that.
What's the limit of the poetical?
How do you read what is not yet writing?
All those kind of questions were
the ones that were placed by by Claudio.
And I really enjoy it,
because when we think about the future
of language,
you know, we think, for instance,
about communication,
as mentioned before with the Rodolfo Mata.
But we think as well about identity,
like how this affects identity,
like in other terms,
like how can we make AI to, to reply to,
to us, for us, you know,
for our own identity development, right.
And not for the corporation?
That is also some sort of awareness
that happened in Tina speech,
you know, that say, okay, it's
going to be like a cooperative identity.
It's like my name is going to be like,
Vinicius Market
CEO not well,
no, we'll be like Inc or, you know,
for for all those that, live once
at least in America or in Mexico
and know the brand, you know,
that is like a
I have a friend that calls one
and he was saying
that his name will change in that way,
that every time that he introduced
himself, he's going to make like
an announcement
like Juancho Caritas is to mo.
You know that.
And I have to say that it's happening
right now.
Every time you open social media,
you don't know if the people is talking to
you or if it's like selling something.
So that's also like
crazy if you think about identity
and writing
or language.
Everybody has their brand.
Yeah, yeah. Precise.
And but I think it's also like a bowling.
Like which brand,
what are you selling or how do you stand.
Where do you stand.
And there's a certain place where like
your, your self as you really are, is,
if you're famous enough,
superseded by the parasocial perception
of who you are that like
the it's the celebrity in the star system.
But the collaborative work there's a the
Victoria Clarkson piece in the exhibition
is one of those works that has quantized
from the quantum keynote last year.
It's a scroll of mission piece by think
Tina is a part of it.
Tina, Mark, Maria, Gorka,
Susana and Carmen Benjamin
Maya
that they're they worked on together.
Just I was reminded of that
when you were talking, when I was talking
about the authority
that the the like combined authorship.
Rate, I
didn't I mean, I hear it,
but I haven't watched it yet,
so we'll just give it here.
Quantum engagement
the lingual is Spanish
English quantum erotica category or.
Well you see she's making her own category
quantum erotica
I like it.
We are quantum quantize
Victoria Clarkson's
We are collective of attack authors,
you see.
Well, I don't know
if somebody wants to play the last one
or I don't know also how we are in time.
We are about to wrap up
since it is 45, so probably.
Oh yeah, yeah,
I see place to stop the stop
and to to say thanks to everybody.
Thanks a lot for joining, for coming,
for contributing for in the experience.
I will work more.
Of course you can
come to to the website and check
all of them in the desktop version.
I think in the few days
I will upload the translations, you know,
but in the desktop version
is completely different experience
because you can see the video, so
you see the people that change a lot also.
So probably I should start by that.
Just sit visit the website
and thanks a lot
for your time
and for participating on the project.
I yeah, I want to thank you again.
That was great.
I'm going to try it outside
when I am able to walk.
I know the rain has ended.
My dog wants to get out there.
I did want to give her a minder
that at six
we do have our evening break,
but at 7 p.m.
there's
going to be the night to performances
and it looks like a really great event.
So thank you again.
Thanks a lot Anastasia.
Thank you.
That was great session.
Everything.
We have
our dinner break in the conference time.
So and I will see you all back
on this track at seven
which was.
Chow chow.
Goodbye. Thank you.